Paul Howard Ezell papers, 1939-1987
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Paul Howard Ezell papers, 1939-1987
MS 282
Ezell, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1913-1988
Arranged in six series: Biographical Information. Diaries and Record Books, 1939-1964. General Correspondence, 1958-1975. Writings and Reviews, 1950- 1987. Project Files, 1951-1982. Pima Land Claim Case Files, 1683-1974. arrangement varies by series. The bulk of the collection consists of the Pima Land Claim Case Files, 1683-1974. This includes correspondence with the law firm of Cox and Cox, and Henry F. Dobyns; also transcripts of the court hearings. Background information, in support of claims by the Pima-Maricopa, includes photocopies of primary source material from the Spanish, Mexican, and American periods. The rest of the collection includes various materials relating to Ezell's work and professional interests: diaries, record books, correspondence with colleagues, published and unpublished reports and articles, reviews, drawings, charts, maps of southern Arizona, microfilms, audiotapes, black-and-white photographs, negatives, and color slides.
7.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Paul Howard Ezell was born 12 August 1913 on a homestead in Carbon County, Wyoming and moved west to Davis, California, with his parents around 1925. From Davis, he came to the University of Arizona, where he obtained his master's degree in archaeology in 1939 and his PhD. in 1956. His dissertation, The Hispanic Acculturation of the Gila River Pimas, was published in 1961 as Memoir no. 90 of the American Anthropological Association ( American Anthropologist, vol. 63, no. 5, part 2).
For a time, Ezell was field foreman on a W.P.A. archaeology project in North Carolina, but in 1941, he was accepted into the Immigration Border Patrol at El Paso, Texas. In 1943, he entered the Navy as a gunnery officer, returning to the Border Patrol in Ajo, Arizona, after his stint. There, he used his time to note the occurrence of archaeological sites.
In the 1950s and 1960s, Ezell worked for the Pima-Maricopa Indian tribe and served as an expert witness, testifying before the Indian Claims Commission in behalf of land claims made by the tribe against the United States government. Toward that end, he examined virtually all of the available material concerning the Pima-Maricopa Indians in the area. He also carried out archaeological surveys and conducted ethnographic and oral history field work among the Pima-Maricopa Indians.
Archaeological and historical studies of the Indians of southern Arizona, southern California, northern Sonora, and northern Baja California were Ezell's major interests during his career, along with field work in Bolivia and archaeological excavations at the Spanish presidio of San Diego.
Ezell died of cancer in his San Diego home 29 July 1988.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series:
Series I: Biographical Information, 1959-1987
Series II: Project Files, 1951-1982
Series III: Pima Land Claim Case Files, 1683-1974
Scope and Content Note
The Papers in the first four series include Biographical Information; Ezell's Diaries and Record Books from 1939-1964, detailing events and information relevant to his activities with the United States Border Patrol, his pilot flight record and log book, his archaeological activities, and his work with the Pima-Maricopa Indian tribe; General Correspondence, chiefly between Ezell and his professional contemporaries, from 1958-1975; and Writings and Reviews written by Ezell and others, including published and unpublished manuscripts and journal articles from 1950-1987.
The fifth series, Project Files from 1951 to 1982, contains information on Organ Pipe National Monument and Painted Rock Reservoir, including material on Lower Colorado buff ware and pottery types by site locations as well as hand drawings of pottery designs, combinations, and elements; and information about a W.P.A. archaeological project in North Carolina for which Ezell served as a field supervisor in 1941.
The last series, Pima Land Claim Case Files from 1683-1974, contains extensive material on the Pima Land Claims Case for which Ezell served as an expert witness. Included are correspondence, both of a general nature and more specifically between Ezell and lawyers Z. Simpson Cox and Alfred S. Cox; transcripts of the court hearings; background materials which include information in support of Ezell's work to substantiate the land claims of the Pima-Maricopa tribe; reports containing photocopies of primary source materials which were used as exhibits in Ezell's efforts to describe a tract of land which he considered to have been used exclusively by the Pima-Maricopa Indians; and research files containing photocopies of primary source material from the Spanish, Mexican, and American periods concerning the Pima-Maricopa Indians in Arizona. These research files are followed by microfilms and audiotapes.
The bulk of the microfilm contains copies of original source materials from the Bancroft Library at the University of California, the Arizona Historical Society, the Library of Congress, the National Archives, Archivo General de la Nacion, the Escuela Nacional de Antropologia Biblioteca, the Biblioteca Nacional Archivo Franciscano, and the Archivo General y Publico. Ezell's indexes to the materials on microfilm are also included. Many of the photocopies and English translations in the research files were made from information contained on these microfilm rolls. The five reel-to-reel magnetic tapes contain Pima, Papago, Yaqui, and Mexican Indian music, an interview done by Ezell of Maricopa Indian Cyrus Sunn on 13 August 1957, and a word list given by Kisto Morago of Sacaton, Arizona, using the word list furnished by Roger Nedry in his work on the Papago. The cassette tape is primarily a discussion of the artifacts and aboriginal tribes of Australia with Norman Tindale.
The photographic materials include 14 black and white photographs, most of which were taken in 1957 at places occupied by the Pima-Maricopa Indians. Also included are twenty-seven miscellaneous negatives. The bulk of the fifty-two color slides document the burial site of Father Eusebio Kino and missions in Arizona and Sonora. The maps are primarily of southern Arizona and northern Sonora (Pimeria Alta) and contain historical and cultural information relevant to the Pima-Maricopa Indians.
Ezell, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1913-1988 -- Archives; Ezell, Greta S.; Dobyns, Henry F. -- Correspondence; Celaya, Alberto -- Interviews; Sunn, Cyrus -- Interviews; Messrs. Cox and Co. -- Correspondence; Gila River Pima-Maricopa Indian Community -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Pima Indians -- Claims; Maricopa Indians -- Claims; Indians of North America -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Arizona; Indians of North America -- Southwest, New -- History -- Chronology; Ethnohistory -- Arizona; United States -- Trials, litigation, etc; Southwest, New -- History -- Sources; Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources; Painted Rocks Reservoir (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources; Correspondence; Journals; Photographs; Reports; Interviews; Maps
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Information, 1939-1987
  - Subseries I: Biographical Information, 1959-1987
    Contains three cassette tapes of Paul and Greta Ezell as interviewed by Bill Broyles on 16 and 17 October l987 at the Ezells' home in Pacific Beach, California. This interview served as the framework for "Desert Archaeology: An Interview with Paul H. Ezell, 1913-1988," which was published in the Journal of the Southwest, vol. 30, no. 3, Autumn 1988, pp. 398-449. Although the contents of the tapes were edited and rearranged for publication, the article is nevertheless a reasonable substitute for a transcript. Also contains miscellaneous professional and retirement information, including a survey of Ezell's investigations in progress in the field of Latin American studies, a report of his research, and a curriculum vitae dated October 1980.
    - Biographical information. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Interview, Paul and Greta Ezell by Bill Broyles. October 16-17, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subseries II: Diaries and Record Books, 1939-1964
    Contains eight diaries and other record books relevant to Ezell's vocational activities. Included are portions of an address book, site notes and miscellaneous notes dated 1939 and 1955, two diaries covering 1946-1948 when Ezell worked for the U.S. Border Patrol, a daily log of the University of Arizona Archaeological Field School at Point of Pines, Arizona written by Ezell during the summer of 1949, a field book describing his work in the Papago lands between 1951 and 1955, a time record on the Pima Maricopa claim from 1955-1960, a 1957 pilot flight record and log book which contains some site notes relevant to Ezell's trip from San Diego to Gila Bend in December 1957, and a diary of Ezell's field work on the Pima Land Case from April 1957 - February 1964. Included in this diary is information regarding Ezell's interview with Maricopa Indian Cyrus Sunn on 13 August 1957. A tape recording of this interview can be found in the Audiovisual Materials Series in Boxes 16 and 17; however, no transcript is available.
    - Portions of address book; site notes and misc. 1939, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - U.S. Immigration Border Patrol, Ajo, Arizona. 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - University of Arizona Archaeological Field School, Point of Pines, Arizona. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Field book, Papago lands. 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Time Record on Pima Maricopa Claim." August 29, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Pilot flight record and log book. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Diaries. 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subseries III: General Correspondence, 1952-1982
    Contains letters between Paul Ezell and his professional contemporaries, chiefly regarding work-related activities and projects. Correspondents include Charles L. Camp, Wallace L. Chafe, Henry F. Dobyns, Bernard Fontana, Eugene E. Gage, Ronald L. Ives, Alfonso Ortiz, Albert H. Schroeder, and Marie Wormington. Also includes correspondence regarding Ezell's work on and publication of a catalog of the Aguiar collection for the Arizona Historical Society.
    - General correspondence. 1958-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Aguiar collection in the Arizona Pioneer Historical Society. 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IV: Writings and reviews, 1950-1987
    Contains typed and handwritten copies of Ezell's manuscripts, both published and unpublished, as well as manuscripts by Goode P. Davis, Robert A. Hackenberg, Gertrude Hill, Michael B. and Barbara B. Stanislawski, and Clara Lee Tanner. Most of the manuscripts are concerned with Ezell's archaeologic and ethnohistoric interests in southern Arizona, northern Sonora, northern Baja, and southern California. Also included are three manuscripts, possibly by Ezell, which discuss post-Pleistocene changes in the Gila-Sonoran zone, archaeological conservation teams for the Bureau of Indian Affairs, and tribal groups in the Phoenix area, and searches for evidence of early man in playas. Ten critiques of books which Ezell wrote for the Garland American Indian Ethnohistory series comprise the bulk of the reviews. Salvage Archaeology in the Chama Valley of New Mexico, 1450-1700, and the book Earlier Than You Think, by George F. Carter, are among other monographs evaluated.
    - Writings by Paul H. Ezell
      - Aboriginal Pot Mending in Southern California. No Date (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Physiography of the Sonoran Section of the Basin and Range Province. 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - An Artifact of Human Bone from Eastern Arizona, by P.H. Ezell and Alan P. Olson. 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - The Archaeological Delineation of a Cultural Boundary in Papagueria. 1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Indians Under the Law - Mexico, 1821-1847. 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Ecology and Image: Pima-Papago Contrasts. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - The Hispanic Acculturation of the Gila River Pimas. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Pima Bibliography. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Death of a Society, by H.F. Dobyns, P.H. Ezell, G.S. Ezell and Alden W. Jones. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Is There a Hohokam-Pima Culture Continuum? 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - The Maricopas: An Identification from Documentary sources. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - The Case of the Orurillo "Cannibals." 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Blood Groups in the American Southwest: Some methodological considerations of interpretations. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Background to Battle: Circumstances Relating to Death on the Gila,1857, by P.H. Ezell and G.S. Ezell. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Plants Without Water, Drafts. No Date (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Plants Without Water: The Pima-Maricopa Experience. 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - The Sherds from 4 RIV 149. 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Ballcourt or Reservoir? 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Cosoy Revisited. 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Sedelmayr's Letter of 1744, by P.H. and G.S. Ezell. 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Sedelmayr's Letter of 1744, in Spanish, withaccompanying English translation by the Ezells. 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Post-Pleistocene Changes in the Gila-Sonoran Zone, possibly by P.H. Ezell? No Date (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Pots, Skeletons, and Arrowpoints: An Exercise in Logic, possibly by P.H. Ezell? No Date (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Proposal for Archaeological Conservation Teams for the Bureau of Indian Affairs and Tribal Groups Phoenix, Arizona, possibly by P.H. Ezell? No Date (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Untitled manuscript, possibly by P.H. Ezell? No Date (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Writings by Other Authors
      - Papago Legends from Santa Rosa, Arizona-II, by Gertrude Hill. 1940 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Identification Marks on Hopi and Tewa Pottery; Hopi and Tewa Ceramic Tradition Networks, by Michael B. and Barbara B. Stanislawski. 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Ecological Change and Economic Adjustment on the Gila River Indian Reservation, by Robert A. Hackenberg. 1974 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
      - Ecological Change and Economic Adjustment on the Gila River Indian Reservation, by Robert A. Hackenberg. 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Man and Wildlife in Arizona: The Pre-Settlement Era, 1824-1865, by Goode P. Davis. 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Southwestern Indian Watercolors, by Clara Lee Tanner. No Date (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Turkey Domestication, unknown author. No Date (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Reviews by Paul H. Ezell
      - "Salvage Archaeology in the Chama Valley, New Mexico." 1953? (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Garland American Indian Ethnohistory Series. Also includes correspondence between Ezell and Katherine M. Weist, Book Review Editor. 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Earlier Than You Think. c. 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Comments on Dobyns' and Nicklason's papers on the Pimas and Maricopas. c. 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - The Protohistoric Period in the American Southwest, 1450-1700. c. 1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series II: Project Files, 1941-1982
  Contains information pertaining to various archaeological surveys in which Ezell participated, including Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument, where Ezell served as the National Park Service collaborator, and Painted Rock Reservoir, where he worked with National Park Service archaeologist Albert H. Schroeder. Also contains material about Lower Colorado buff ware, including ceramic distribution information, organization notes, a manuscript by Greta Ezell commenting on the Painted Rocks Reservoir Survey, source material, and a trait chart. Also contains information about a W.P.A. archaeological project at the University of North Carolina where Ezell served as field supervisor in 1941. Included in the project files are background source materials, correspondence, site information, maps, reports, and photographs pertinent to each endeavor.
  - Subseries I: Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument, 1951-1973, No Date
    - Arizona State Museum site cards. No Date (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Artifacts information. c. 1958 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Background source materials. No Date (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Chipped Stone Tools from the Sierra Pinacate, manuscript by Eleanor Jane Rosenthal. 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence. 1951-1954 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence. 1954-1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - List of OPCNM Collections at San Diego. No Date (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Maps. 1952 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Report. c. 1954 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Site records. No Date (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Survey card list. c. 1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - #Oversize folder found at end of collection. Kinship charts and pottery types by site locations pertaining to Organ Pipe, 25 sheets. No Date (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - #Oversize folder found at end of collection. Hand drawings of pottery designs, combinations, and elements pertaining to Snaketown, 33 sheets. No Date (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Subseries II: Painted Rock Reservoir, 1956-1962, No Date
    - Background on sites and surrounding areas. No Date (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, Correspondents include Albert H. Schroeder and Henry F. Dobyns. 1957-1960 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Ethnic locations. No Date (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Final - Archaeological Survey of Painted Rock Reservoir, manuscript and correspondence. 1961 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Historical introduction for survey report. 1959 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - The Indigenous Population, manuscript. No Date (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Photographs. 1956 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Painted Rock report and Pima claim. 1962 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Source notes. No Date (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Comments by G.S. Ezell on part of Documentary Evidence Pertaining to the Early Historic Period of Southern Arizona by Albert H. Schroeder. 1958 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Trait chart, Lower Colorado buff ware. No Date (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Ceramic distributions, Lower Colorado buffware. No Date (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Comments on the Ceramics of the Painted Rocks Reservoir Survey conducted by Schroeder and Ezell, manuscript by G.S. Ezell, and organization notes. c. 1961 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Source material (on cards and not yet on cards), Lower Colorado buff ware. 1958 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Subseries III: W.P.A. Archaeological Project, 1941
    - University of North Carolina. 1941 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Series III: Pima Land Claim Case Files, 1541-1974
  Contains correspondence, transcripts, background materials, reports, research files, microfilms and audiotapes, photographic materials, and maps which pertain to the Pima Land Claim Case. Ezell served as the principal expert witness for the Gila River Pima-Maricopa Indian Community in this case, and the items in this series include ethnographic and historical accounts, informants' statements and other reports and information concerning the early Pima and Maricopa Indians which were used in the case in an attempt to show that the Indians held title to the land in question.
  - Subseries I: Correspondence, 1952-1974
    Principal correspondents include Henry F. Dobyns and lawyers Z. Simpson Cox, Alfred S. Cox, Charles McPhee Wright, and Samuel P. Goddard, Jr.
    - General, A-L. 1952-1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - General, M-Z. 1952-1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Cox and Cox. 1951-1959 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Cox and Cox. 1960-1969 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Cox and Cox. 1970-1974 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II: Transcripts, 1951-1974
    The bulk of the transcripts concern reports and testimony given before the Indian Claims Commission. Hearings on the claim were held from July 23-August 10, l962. The findings of the commission were presented on 17 December 1970. Additional findings of fact were decided on 20 January 1972. Also included is a transcript in Spanish of an interview of Alberto Celaya by Ezell in 1952. Mr. Celaya, of Sonoita, Sonora, served as a guide for Carl Lumholtz for six months of the latter's travels in parts of Papagueria in 1909 and 1910.
    - Transcript of Interview of Alberto Celaya by Paul Ezell. 1952 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Transcript of Arenenos - Celaya and history. 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Transcript of trial, Cox and Cox. 1957-1974 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Transcript of trial, Cox and Cox. 1957-1974 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries III: Background materials, 1541-1970s
    The background materials files contain a copy of the instructions given to Hernando de Alarcon by Viceroy Don Antonio de Mendoza in 1541, a photocopy of the original document from the Department of the Interior advising of a Congressional appropriation of $200,000 to build a wagon road from El Paso to Fort Yuma, photocopies of Alphonse Pinart's "Voyage dans l'Arizona" and "Voyage en Sonora," accompanied by Helen Hayden's unfinished translations of those works, a photocopy of "Informe Sobre Una Excursion a la Baja California" by Jorge Engerrand, accompanied by an English translation.
    - Instructions to Hernando de Alarcon from Viceroy Don Antonio de Mendoza. 1541 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - United States. Dept. of Interior. El Paso to Fort Yuma wagon road. 1857 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "Voyage dans l'Arizona," and "Voyage en Sonora," by Alphonse Pinart. 1877, 1880 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - "Informe Sobre Una Excursion a la Baja California," by Jorge Engerrand, original and translation. 1913 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Exhibitions lists, notes. 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Thirteenth Cause Paper, "The Destruction of Pima Culture as a Basis for Legal Action." 1954 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Professional affairs, contracts, et al. 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Indian Claims. 1959 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Research notes; miscellaneous. 1960s (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IV: Reports, 1683-1974
    The reports contain primarily photocopies of source documents which were used as court exhibits in the Pima Land Claims Case. Among the reports, a copy of the deposition of noted ethnologist Frederick W. Hodge, given before the Indian Claims Commission on 17 Feb. 1956, can be found.
    - Reports. 1683-1699 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Reports. 1700-1774 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Reports. 1775-1776 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Reports. 1777-1799 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Reports. 1800-1825 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Reports. 1826-1849 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Reports. 1850-1859 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Reports. 1860-1869 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Reports. 1870-1879 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Reports. 1880-1885 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Reports. 1886-1899 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Reports. 1900-1910 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Reports. 1911-1924 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Reports. 1925-1929 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Reports. 1930-1934 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Reports. 1935 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Reports. 1936-1938 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Reports. 1939-1949 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Reports. 1950-1955 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Reports. 1956-1969 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Reports. 1970-1974 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Reports. 1974 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Subseries V: Research files, 1698-1956